Guide to the C. L. R. James papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
C. L. R. James Papers,
1933-2001
[Bulk Dates: 1948-1989].
James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.
23.51 linear ft. 44 boxes (18 document boxes, 22 record storage cartons, 4 oversized flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1529
6910705
These papers contain correspondence; drafts, manuscripts and notes; transcripts of lectures and interviews; printed material; photographs; and audio and video tapes related to life and work of West Indian native C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert) James-- an athlete, scholar, teacher, writer and political activist.
Biographical Note
West Indian native C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert) James was an athlete, scholar, teacher, writer and political activist. James, known affectionately since childhood as Nello, was born in 1901 in Tunapuna, Trinidad. His father, Robert Alexander James, was a schoolmaster; his mother Ida Elizabeth (Bessie) Rudder James, a native of Barbados, was a home-maker. James, the eldest of three siblings, had one sister, Olive, and a brother, Eric. In 1910, at the age of nine, James won an "exhibition" or scholarship to Queen's Royal College (QRC)--located in Port-of-Spain--which he entered in 1911. James' formal education ended in 1918 upon receipt of his "school certificate" from QRC.
Through the 1920s James taught school, played cricket and wrote. His teaching stints included work at QRC where Eric Williams, future Prime Minister of Trinidad and Tobago, was among his pupils. James played cricket with the Maples, a Port-of-Spain club team, and was a member of the Maverick, a local literary society. In 1929 James married Juanita Samuel Young, a native of Venezuela who worked as a stenographer. In 1932 he left for Britain alone.
James lived with Cricket star, Learie Constantine, and his wife Norma in Nelson, Lancashire, upon arriving in Britain. He picked up work as a sports writer, covering cricket matches, for the Manchester Guardian. In 1934 James moved to London where he joined the Independent Labor Party (ILP), wrote for its journal, New Leader, and honed his skills as a speaker at ILP rallies. In London James met George Padmore and renewed his ties to his former student, Eric Williams. James also attended the founding conference of the Fourth International in Paris in 1938.
Although James had published a few pieces in small literary journals Trinidad and The Beacon, and one short story, "La Divina Pastora," in The Saturday Evening Post in 1927, his career as a writer did not take off until he reached England. His literary accomplishments during these years included: a novel, Minty Alley, published in 1936; his play, Toussaint L'Oueverture opened in London, also in 1936, starring Paul Robeson; and The Black Jacobins, a history of the slave rebellion in Santo Domingo, which was led by Toussaint L'Oueverture, was published in 1938.
In 1938, with Leon Trotsky advocating for the Socialist Workers Party's (SWP) to address the "Negro Question" and at the invitation of James Cannon from the American wing of the SWP, James left London for a speaking tour of the United States. James traveled to Mexico in 1939 for a meeting with Trotsky. The six-month-long cross-country tour turned into a fifteen-year sojourn and although James remained long in the United States, his time with the SWP was short.
A rift among members of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) led to the creation of the Workers Party (WP) in 1940, and within the WP, the Johnson-Forest Tendency. Johnson and Forest of the Tendency were James, who wrote as J.R. Johnson, and Dunayevskaya, who assumed the moniker of Freddie Forest. James and Dunayevskaya were soon joined in their political, philosophical and writing endeavors by Grace Lee, whose pseudonym was Ria Stone. In 1947 the Johnson-Forest Tendency rejoined the SWP briefly, but by 1951 the Johnson-Forest Tendency was independent of both the SWP and the WP. James and Dunayevskaya wrote the Balance Sheet Completed, to explain their decision to finally leave the SWP and they established the Correspondence Publishing Committee, which published a mimeographed newsletter, Correspondence. Among the members of the Correspondence Publishing Committee were James Boggs, who was by then the husband of Grace Lee; Freddy and Lyman Paine; Filomena Daddario (Finch); and Morris Goelman (William Gorman). In 1955 Raya Dunayevskaya left Correspondence to form the News & Letters Committee. Yet another division occurred in 1962 when James, along with Martin Glaberman, broke with Correspondence to create the Facing Reality Group; James Boggs and Grace Lee Boggs, and Freddy and Lyman Paine remained with Correspondence. Facing Reality, whose official organ was Speak Out, disbanded in 1970. Some of the materials James wrote and collaborated on with these various groups included: The Balance Sheet (1947); The Invading Socialist Society (1947); The Revolutionary Answer to the Negro Problem in the USA (1948); Notes on Dialectics (1948); and State Capitalism and World Revolution (1950).
During his extended stay in the United States James was based in New York City where he developed friendships with Richard Wright and his wife, Ellen; Chester Himes; and Ralph Ellison among others.
In 1946 James married Constance Webb, whom he had first met during his speaking tour in 1939 and with whom he had corresponded ever since. Due to complications around James' divorce from Juanita James, the marriage proved to be invalid. They re-married in 1948, after James spent six weeks in Nevada formalizing the divorce from his first marriage. (From Nevada, James wrote extensively to Dunayevskaya and Lee; these letters became the basis of Notes on Dialectic.) In 1949 C. L. R. James, Jr., "Nobbie", the only child of Webb and James, was born. James was charged with passport violations and interned, by the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service, on Ellis Island in 1952. While there he wrote Mariners, Renegades and Castaways (1953), a study of Herman Melville's Moby Dick. In 1953, facing deportation, James left the United States for England; Webb remained in New York with their son.
Brooklyn-born Selma Weinstein (sister of Correspondence member Cecelia Lang), and her young son Sam Weinstein, joined James in London in 1955; James and Selma Weinstein married in 1956.
Returning to London in the mid-1950s allowed James to renew his contacts with Kwame Nkrumah, whom he had met in the United States in 1943, and George Padmore along with others involved in the Pan-African Movement. In 1957 James traveled to Ghana for the country's first independence celebrations, his first trip to Africa. In the 1958 James and Selma left London for Trinidad, where they remained until 1962. During this time James edited The Nation, the paper of the Peoples National Movement (PNM). In 1962, shortly before returning to London, James was severely injured and concussed in a car accident in Trinidad. Modern Politics (1960) and Party Politics in the West Indies (1962) were published during James' time in Trinidad. Back in Britain, James completed Beyond a Boundary (1963), a study of cricket. In 1965 James once again traveled to Trinidad, this time as to report on cricket matches for several British papers. He was promptly, albeit briefly, put under house arrest by the PNM-led government. Once released James helped organize the Workers and Farmers Party of Trinidad and Tobago.
Late in the 1960s James made lecture tours of the United States, Canada and Africa. In 1970 C.L.R. James began teaching at Federal City College in Washington, D.C. where he stayed most of the decade.
In the last two decades of James' life several people served as his assistants, with the primary goal of completing the autobiography that he had begun in the 1970s. Teresa (Teri) Turner was his assistant for a few years in the 1970s; Jim Murray, who had been introduced to James by Paul Buhle, worked for James in 1983; and anthropologist Anna Grimshaw was James' last assistant, from late 1983 until his death in 1989. The autobiography was never completed. In 1984 James withdrew from public speaking, although he still granted some interviews. James died in 1989.
Scope and Content
These papers contain correspondence; drafts, manuscripts and notes; transcripts of lectures and interviews; printed material; photographs; and audio and video tapes related to life and work of West Indian native C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert) James-- an athlete, scholar, teacher, writer and political activist.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eight series
Series I: Correspondence, 1952-1990, Undated
Series II: Writings, 1948-1990, Undated
Subseries II.1. Full-length Works, 1948-1980s, Undated
Subseries II.2. Drafts, Proposals, Reviews, 1966-1980, Undated
Subseries II.3. Lectures and Talks, 1958-1991, 2000, Undated
Subseries II.4. Interviews, circa 1970s-1996, Undated
Subseries II.5. Writings by Others--Drafts and Manuscripts, 1969-1990s, Undated
Series III: Johnson Forest Tendency through Facing Reality, 1943-1972, Undated
Subseries III.1. General, 1946-1972
Subseries III.2. Printed Material, 1943-1969
Series IV: Printed Material, 1933-1992, Undated
Subseries IV.1. Pamphlets, 1933-1992, Undated
Subseries IV.2. General, 1940s-1980s
Series V: Teaching, circa 1970-1981
Series VI: Subject files, 1952-1992
Subseries VI.1. About C.L.R. James, 1966-1992
Subseries VI.2. Personal, 1952-1989
Subseries VI.3. General, 1957-1986
Series VII: Photographs and Audio / Visual Material, 1940s-2001
Subseries VII.1. Photographs, 1940s-2001
Subseries VII.2. Audio / Visual, 1970s-2001
Series VIII: Books From James's Library
Subjects
C. L. R. James Institute.; Correspondence Publishing Committee/Company.; Facing Reality Publishing Committee.; Race Today Collective.; Johnson-Forest Tendency.; Grimshaw, Anna.; Howe, Darcus.; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.; Johnson, J. R., 1901-1989.; Webb, Constance.; West Indies.; Race Relations--London (England).
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
C.L.R. James Estate Gift 2007-2009
Robert Hill, Literary executor
Selected Related Material at Columbia
Margaret Busby Papers, 1978-1989 Columbia University Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anna Grimshaw Papers, 1939-2004 Columbia University Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Darcus Howe Papers, 1965-2008 Columbia University Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Constance Webb Papers, 1918-2005 Columbia University Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Selected Related Material at Other Repositories
Leon Trotsky Exile Papers Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA
C.L.R. James Letters, 1939-1981 New York Public Library, Schomburg Center, New York, NY
Oral History of the American Left: Radical Histories New York University, Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, New York, NY
James and Grace Lee Boggs Papers, 1930s-1993 Wayne State University, Walter P. Reuther Library, Detroit, MI
Raya Dunayevskaya Papers Wayne State University, Walter P. Reuther Library, Detroit, MI
Martin and Jessie Glaberman Papers Wayne State University, Walter P. Reuther Library, Detroit, MI
Frances D. and G. Lyman Paine Papers Wayne State University, Walter P. Reuther Library, Detroit, MI
C. L. R. James Collection University of the West Indies, West Indiana and Special Collections, St. Augustine, Trinidad
- Series I: Correspondence, 1952-1990, Undated
  James corresponded with a wide swath of individuals—heads-of-state and political radicals; established scholars and intellectuals, and students; as well as family and friends. The correspondence in this series reflects that wide-range of correspondents; the number of letters exchanged with any one individual represented here, however, tends to be small. The largest cache of correspondence in this series is between Robert Hill and James.
  The topics within the correspondence are wide-ranging as well: the letters of the 1950s are full of references to American politics, popular culture, and the writings of Melville; by the 1960s more of James' correspondence concerns political movements in the West Indies and in Africa; and most of the 1970s correspondence is related to teaching, invitations to conferences and requests to give talks or lectures.
  - General
    - 1952, 1957, 1961-1964, 1966-1969 (5 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Incoming, 1970-1986, undated (7 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 6 to 12)
    - Incoming--Cards, circa 1970s-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Outgoing, 1970-1987, Undated (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 14 to 17)
    - Outgoing--Dictations, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Facts, Statement of, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alphabetical
    - Addai-Sebo, A. K. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bell, Daniel, 1953 Mar (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Berger, John, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Birnberg, B. M. & Co.--Regarding Selma James, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Boggs, Grace Lee--regarding Melville, 1951 Apr (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Buhle, Paul, 1969-1973, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Clarke, Leroy, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Daddario, Filomena, 1957-1958, 1961, 1976, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Editor, Letters to the, 1963, 1967, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Geismar, Max, 1953, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Glaberman, Martin, 1961-1983 (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Gorman, William, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Guerin, Daniel, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Guevara, Che--Regarding, circa 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Harris, Wilson, 1964--1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Hill, Robert, 1971-1990 (6 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 15 to 20)
    - Kravitz, Nellie, 1963 Mar (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lamming, George, 1957, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Manley, Norman and Michael, 1957-1961, 1977, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Mariners, Renegades and Castaways--from Lewis Mumford, Lionel Trilling, and Mark Van Doren, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Meksin, Isa-Kae, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Murray, Jim, 1981-1990, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 26 to 27)
    - Naipaul, V. S. 1962, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Nkrumah, Kwame, 1957, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Paine, Lyman, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - [Robinson, ANR], Arthur--regarding PNM (People's National Movement) Tribunal, 1961 Mar (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Turner, Terisa, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Webb, Constance and Robert, Jr.--1956-1957 Undated (photocopies) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Webb, Constance and Robert, Jr., 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Webb, Constance and Robert, Jr.--Letters to Nobbie, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - [Williams, Eric] "Bill", 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series II: Writings, 1948-1990s, Undated
  Included in this series are drafts and manuscripts, transcripts of lectures and interviews, and printed material by or about C.L.R. James.
  - Subseries II.1: Full-length works, 1948-1980s, Undated
    This series contains both typescript manuscripts (1950) and printed versions (1956) of American Civilization; drafts and fragments-- a few of which have been heavily annotated by James--of the autobiography that was incomplete at his death; his play Black Jacobins, with hand-written notes by director Dexter Lyndersay; and many of the original letters from James that were the basis of Notes on a Dialectic, along with drafts and materials that have been annotated and edited by James, and a typescript of the monograph. Also here is a typescript version of Notes on the Life of George Padmore and a piece on Shakespeare.
    - Bibliographies, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - American Civilization
      - Proposal, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Introduction--by Martin Glaberman, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Notes on American Civilization--Typescripts, circa 1950, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 8 to 10)
      - The American Civilization--Printed, circa 1956, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 11 to 13)
      - The American Civilization--Printed, circa 1956 (Annotated) (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - The American Civilization--Views of--Printed, circa 1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Autobiography / Biography
      - Timelines, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Outlines, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Introduction--Paul Buhle, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Section 1, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1932-1938 circa 1970s-1980s (Annotated by James) (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1918-1953 circa 1970s-1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 8 to 10)
      - 1968-End, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Last Chapter, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Fragments and Notes, circa 1970s-1980s (Annotated by James) (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Chronological--Photocopies, circa 1970s-1980s, (5 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 14 to 18)
      - Cesaire, Aime, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Education--Early, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Garvey, Marcus, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Gupta, B. K., circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Intellectual Development to 1932 circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Lahr, Charlie, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Parents, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Revolution in the 20th Century, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Robeson, Paul, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Shakespeare, William, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Share Croppers in Missouri, Organizing, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Texas, University at Austin--Episode, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Trotsky, Leon, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - United States, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - United States--Visit to the South in 1939 circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - [Wicks], Harry, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Wright, Richard, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Women, circa 1970s-1980s (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 11 to 13)
    - The Black Jacobins--A Play
      - Act I-Epilogue, 1967 (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 14 to 15)
      - "From the Playwright", circa 1960s (includes notes from the director, Dexter Lyndersay) (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Prologue and Notes, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Toussaint L' Ouverture--Typescript, Undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Appendix--Annotated, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Notes on Dialectic--Drafts, Circa 1948
      The Notes on Dialectic Manuscript is extremely fragile; access to this material is at the discretion of the Curator of Manuscripts.
      - Doctrine of the Notion--1-41 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Leninism and the Notion--42-71 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - The Universal of 1948--72-87 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Trotskyism: Synthetic Cognition--88-99 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - The Absolute Idea--100-119 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Part II--The Doctrine of Being--120-132 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - The Doctrine of Essence--133-176 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Review and Leninist Interlude--177-182c (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Appearance and Reality--182m-206 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Notes on Dialectic--1-4 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Understanding--5-11 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Some Historical Observations on Understanding--12-44 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - The Natural Moments of Thought--45-65 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - The Object of Investigation--81-125 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - The Leap--120-139 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Dialectic in Action--140-142 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - The French Revolution in Historical Logic--143-148 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Part II--153-158 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Part III--159-201 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Practice and Epilogue--202-214 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Typescript--Annotated, circa 1948-1949 (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Notes on Dialectic--Correspondence and Notes, circa 1948-1949 (5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 3 to 6)
      - Comments by Sam Weinstein, Undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Padmore, George--Notes on the Life of--Typescript, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Shakespeare, Undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Subseries II.2: Drafts, Proposals, Reviews, 1966-1980, Undated
    Included here are several shorter pieces on a range of topics: Pan-Africanism, popular culture, reviews as well as brief portraits of several individuals including George Lamming, Kwame Nkrumah and Paul Robeson. Also in this subseries are extracts from James' writings and the writings of others.
    - After Frank Worrell, What?, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Black Struggles, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Cricket, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Dubois, W.E.B., Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Free Press, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Grenada, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Lamming, George, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Mariners, Renegades and Castaways--Afterward, Circa 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Nkrumah, Kwame--Various, 1966-1967, 1978, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Robeson, Paul, Undated (Annotated) (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Superman and the A Bomb, Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Towards the Seventh [Pan-African Conference], circa 1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - West Indian Character--British Connections, Undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Woman, A Modern, Undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Drafts--Fragments (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Extracts, Circa 1960s-1970s (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 16 to 17)
    - Proposals, Circa 1960s, 1970s, Undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Reviews
      - Movies, circa 1970 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Writings, circa 1970s, Undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Writings--V.S. Naipaul, circa 1980 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - By Others--Toussaint L' Ouverture, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Subseries II.3: Lectures and Talks, 1958-1991, 2000, Undated
    This series contains informal talks, conference presentations, lectures, and radio or television broadcasts covering a range of subjects including, but not limited to, literature and literary figures, history, and the Caribbean. The lectures and talks are arranged by title or topic; if untitled, the pieces are arranged by the organization or group to whom the talk was given. The bulk of the material here consists of transcripts of the lectures, or of the recordings of the lectures, and includes printed versions, carbon copies, and photocopies. Two lectures by others, Frank Campbell and Rodney Walter, are here as well.
    - Introduction to C L R James, Undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Africa, 1984, Undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - America, C L R James Reflects on, 1981, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - American Society Today, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - The Artist in the Caribbean, Undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Black Jacobins--1971--Printed, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Black People in Urban Areas in the United States, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Black Power and Black Struggles--Three Lectures, Circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Black Power: Its Past, Today, and the Way Ahead--Printed, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Black Writers Workshop, circa 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Broadcasts, circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Caribbean, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Caribbean Peoples, the Making of, 1966 1968--Printed (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Caribbean Peoples, a National Purpose for, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Civilization, Decline of Western, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Colonial World, The Former, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Constantine, Learie, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Dialectics, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Douglass, Frederick, Undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - From Dubois to Fanon, Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Existentialism to Marxism, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - On Federation--Printed, 1958, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 17)